<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/lectures/default.xsl"?>
<fr:tree xmlns:fr="http://www.forester-notes.org" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xml="http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/namespace" root="false" base-url="/lectures/">
  <fr:frontmatter>
    <fr:authors>
      <fr:author>
        <fr:link href="/lectures/ellieripley/" title="Ellie Ripley" uri="https://negation.rocks/lectures/ellieripley/" display-uri="ellieripley" type="local">Ellie Ripley</fr:link>
      </fr:author>
    </fr:authors>
    <fr:date>
      <fr:year>2026</fr:year>
      <fr:month>3</fr:month>
      <fr:day>23</fr:day>
    </fr:date>
    <fr:uri>https://negation.rocks/lectures/005J/</fr:uri>
    <fr:display-uri>005J</fr:display-uri>
    <fr:route>/lectures/005J/</fr:route>
    <fr:title text="Preservation">Preservation</fr:title>
    <fr:taxon>Definition</fr:taxon>
  </fr:frontmatter>
  <fr:mainmatter>
    <html:p>A connective in a language <html:strong>preserves</html:strong> a property of sentences iff: whenever that connective is the main connective of a sentence, if all the components of that sentence have the property, then so does the sentence itself.</html:p>
  </fr:mainmatter>
  <fr:backmatter>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors />
        <fr:title text="References">References</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter />
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors />
        <fr:title text="Context">Context</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter>
        <fr:tree show-metadata="true" expanded="false" toc="false" numbered="false">
          <fr:frontmatter>
            <fr:authors>
              <fr:author>
                <fr:link href="/lectures/ellieripley/" title="Ellie Ripley" uri="https://negation.rocks/lectures/ellieripley/" display-uri="ellieripley" type="local">Ellie Ripley</fr:link>
              </fr:author>
            </fr:authors>
            <fr:date>
              <fr:year>2026</fr:year>
              <fr:month>3</fr:month>
              <fr:day>22</fr:day>
            </fr:date>
            <fr:uri>https://negation.rocks/lectures/005A/</fr:uri>
            <fr:display-uri>005A</fr:display-uri>
            <fr:route>/lectures/005A/</fr:route>
            <fr:title text="Reasoning by induction">Reasoning by induction</fr:title>
          </fr:frontmatter>
          <fr:mainmatter>
            <html:p>Here it helps to be a bit more precise in a certain kind of ritualised way.
(With all our symbols flying around, this is probably the class where you're most likely to accidentally summon a demon anyhow; let's lean into it!)
The ritualised reasoning I want to introduce here is called reasoning <html:em>by induction</html:em>.</html:p>
            <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
              <fr:frontmatter>
                <fr:authors>
                  <fr:author>
                    <fr:link href="/lectures/ellieripley/" title="Ellie Ripley" uri="https://negation.rocks/lectures/ellieripley/" display-uri="ellieripley" type="local">Ellie Ripley</fr:link>
                  </fr:author>
                </fr:authors>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2026</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>3</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>22</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:uri>https://negation.rocks/lectures/005B/</fr:uri>
                <fr:display-uri>005B</fr:display-uri>
                <fr:route>/lectures/005B/</fr:route>
                <fr:taxon>Side note</fr:taxon>
              </fr:frontmatter>
              <fr:mainmatter>
                <html:p>Actually, there are at least two different kinds of reasoning that get called <html:em>reasoning by induction</html:em>, and they are very much not the same!
One is the kind that plays a role in the so-called <fr:link href="https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/induction-problem/" type="external">"problem of induction"</fr:link>; that's <html:em>not</html:em> what I'm talking about here.
The other is one that's sometimes called "mathematical induction" or "structural induction", and that's what we are doing.</html:p>
              </fr:mainmatter>
            </fr:tree>
            <html:p>The core of the idea is this: suppose we want to securely demonstrate that <html:em>all formulas</html:em> are such-and-such a way.
The idea of induction doesn't depend on <html:em>what</html:em> we're trying to show about all formulas, so for now let's just say we want to show that all formulas are happy.</html:p>
            <html:p>We can use what we know about <fr:link href="/lectures/000G/" title="Languages" uri="https://negation.rocks/lectures/000G/" display-uri="000G" type="local">how formulas are built up</fr:link> to systematically think about all formulas, and make sure we haven't left any of them out.
Since there are <fr:link href="/lectures/000K/" title="Infinity; or, more than about six" uri="https://negation.rocks/lectures/000K/" display-uri="000K" type="local">more than six or seven</fr:link> formulas, we need some kind of system!
The structure of formulas themselves is a very useful system much of the time, and it's what I'll use here.</html:p>
            <html:p>We want to start, then, with the atomic sentences, showing that they are all happy.
In practice, how we do this will depend on what it is we're really showing about all sentences; induction provides us no help here.
But suppose we can do it: we've shown that all atomic sentences are happy.
</html:p>
            <html:p>What remains is all the compound sentences, and this is where induction really gives us its power.
All we need to do here is to show that <html:em>if</html:em> all the components of a compound sentence are happy, <html:em>then</html:em> the compound sentence itself is also happy.
That is, in showing that the compound sentence is happy, we can <html:em>help ourselves</html:em> to the assumption that all its components are happy.
</html:p>
            <html:p>This is important enough that it's handy to have a word for it:</html:p>
            <fr:tree show-metadata="false">
              <fr:frontmatter>
                <fr:authors>
                  <fr:author>
                    <fr:link href="/lectures/ellieripley/" title="Ellie Ripley" uri="https://negation.rocks/lectures/ellieripley/" display-uri="ellieripley" type="local">Ellie Ripley</fr:link>
                  </fr:author>
                </fr:authors>
                <fr:date>
                  <fr:year>2026</fr:year>
                  <fr:month>3</fr:month>
                  <fr:day>23</fr:day>
                </fr:date>
                <fr:uri>https://negation.rocks/lectures/005J/</fr:uri>
                <fr:display-uri>005J</fr:display-uri>
                <fr:route>/lectures/005J/</fr:route>
                <fr:title text="Preservation">Preservation</fr:title>
                <fr:taxon>Definition</fr:taxon>
              </fr:frontmatter>
              <fr:mainmatter>
                <html:p>A connective in a language <html:strong>preserves</html:strong> a property of sentences iff: whenever that connective is the main connective of a sentence, if all the components of that sentence have the property, then so does the sentence itself.</html:p>
              </fr:mainmatter>
            </fr:tree>
            <html:p>So what we're aiming to do is to show that all the connectives <html:em>preserve</html:em> the property of happiness.</html:p>
            <html:p>Think about why this works: suppose it's true that all atomic sentences are happy, and that all the connectives preserve happiness.
How, then, could there ever be a sentence that wasn't happy?
How could it be built?
We have to start from atomic sentences that are happy, and build up using connectives that can't ever bring us from happy sentences to not-happy ones.
So any sentence we can manage to build in this way must be happy---but that's all the sentences!</html:p>
            <html:p>If we can show the two parts of what we need, then:
<html:ul><html:li>that all atomic sentences are happy, and</html:li>
<html:li>that all connectives preserve happiness,</html:li></html:ul>
then we've shown "by induction" that all sentences are happy.</html:p>
          </fr:mainmatter>
        </fr:tree>
      </fr:mainmatter>
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors />
        <fr:title text="Backlinks">Backlinks</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter>
        <fr:tree show-metadata="true" expanded="false" toc="false" numbered="false">
          <fr:frontmatter>
            <fr:authors>
              <fr:author>
                <fr:link href="/lectures/ellieripley/" title="Ellie Ripley" uri="https://negation.rocks/lectures/ellieripley/" display-uri="ellieripley" type="local">Ellie Ripley</fr:link>
              </fr:author>
            </fr:authors>
            <fr:date>
              <fr:year>2026</fr:year>
              <fr:month>3</fr:month>
              <fr:day>29</fr:day>
            </fr:date>
            <fr:uri>https://negation.rocks/lectures/005X/</fr:uri>
            <fr:display-uri>005X</fr:display-uri>
            <fr:route>/lectures/005X/</fr:route>
            <fr:title text="Taking stock">Taking stock</fr:title>
          </fr:frontmatter>
          <fr:mainmatter>
            <html:p>We're now getting to the real work of logic.
Note that there's only one new definition in this lecture!
I think this is the first time we've had so few.
We're rather working with all the definitions we've built up over the preceding weeks, and exploring some of the texture that results.</html:p>
            <html:p>The headlines this time are the strength facts we've shown: K3 is weaker than classical logic, FDE is weaker than LP, FDE is weaker than K3.
(We haven't asked about LP and classical logic, but you now have enough to be able to figure this one out!)</html:p>
            <html:p>More important than these headlines, though, is the techniques we developed on the way there.
First, there is the key way we used matrices: when we have two logics given via matrices, if we can transform any counterexample to an argument in one of these matrices into a counterexample to the same argument in the other matrix, then we can conclude that the second logic is weaker than the first.</html:p>
            <html:p>And second, there is the technique of reasoning by induction that is key for applying this technique to matrices built on different structures.
Here, if we want to show that any property holds of all sentences in our language, we show that it holds for all atomic sentences and that all connectives <fr:link href="/lectures/005J/" title="Preservation" uri="https://negation.rocks/lectures/005J/" display-uri="005J" type="local">preserve</fr:link> the property.
Since all sentences are built from atomics via connectives, this is enough to ensure that every sentence has the property.</html:p>
          </fr:mainmatter>
        </fr:tree>
      </fr:mainmatter>
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors />
        <fr:title text="Related">Related</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter />
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree show-metadata="false" hidden-when-empty="true">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:authors />
        <fr:title text="Contributions">Contributions</fr:title>
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter />
    </fr:tree>
  </fr:backmatter>
</fr:tree>
